Welcome back to A Push in under 3
minutes. No time for intros, let's get
into it. It's been a second since we've
talked about it, so let's head on over
back to the Cold War. Last time we
talked a lot about the Cold War in
Europe and also in the US, but now the
Cold War will expand to all over the
world. Let's first head over to Latin
America. And really quickly, the key
point I want to make here before I talk
about anything is that the US will
support any government that is
anti-communist, even if it's not
democratic. So, over in Guatemala, the
US sees a leader who makes controversial
potentially communist influence land
reform. So, the CIA helps overthrow him.
Over in Chile, a socialist democracy is
made with another democratically elected
guy, and so the US supported his coup
d'état. But, it's not all sunshine and
rainbows. Cuba was a country directly
aligned with the Soviet Union. So, the
US decides to launch an invasion known
as the Bay of Pigs. And through a lot of
reasons, it completely fails. But, now
moving over to Africa and the Middle
East, most of these newly formed
countries try to stay out of the Cold
War, meaning they were, quote,
non-aligned. However, the US still
intervened a bit. The US will help
overthrow a leader in Iran, help
negotiate peace between Egypt and
Israel, and in Angola, there was a proxy
war between the USSR and the US.
Honestly, it's a dang chess match. That
is the best way I can describe the Cold
War. But, unlike a chess match, there
were actual consequences. And that was
the nuclear threat of a fear of
annihilation. That is where a concept of
MAD is declared, which means mutually
assured destruction. Meaning if one side
launches nukes, the other side is going
to do the same. Sure, this does prevent
war, but it will also lead to a massive
arms build-up and debates around America
will spark up about spending in the
military. This will even lead to
Eisenhower warning about the, quote,
military-industrial complex, where he
warned that government plus military
plus corporations held way too much
power in the United States. On the
screen now are AP style questions for
this topic. Pause now.
I'll put the answers on the screen now.
I will see you in the next one.